AFSCME, District Council 37 Photographs PHOTOS.247
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME), District Council 37 Photographs
1946-2003
1967-2000
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
AFSCME. District Council 37 (New York, N.Y.)
Roberts, Lillian
PHOTOS.247
97 Linear Feet 97 boxes
District Council 37, American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees (AFSCME) is an umbrella group of 56 local unions representing public employees in New York City. Chartered in 1944, DC 37 has grown from an organization of less than a thousand employees in the city's parks, hospital, finance, and health departments to the country's largest federation of public employees, with more than 125,000 members working in the city's agencies and cultural institutions. This collection is comprised of black and white photographic prints (the bulk are 8x10), color photographic prints (mainly 4x6 snapshots), contact sheets, negatives, and slides from the Communications Department of AFSCME District Council 37. There are approximately 41,300 photographs and 24,500 contact sheets. The collection contains approximately 422,400 individual negative images. The bulk of individual images are black and white negatives.
Separated Materials
Graphic materials (cartoons, drawings, etc.) have been separated into American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME), District Council 37 Graphics (GRAPHICS 34).
Films have been separated into American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME), District Council 37 Films (FILMS 10).
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees (AFSCME), District Council 37 Records (WAG 265)
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, District Council 37, Local 420 (Hospital Workers) Records (WAG 215)
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, District Council 37, Local 420 (Hospital Workers) Photographs (PHOTOS 212)
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, DC 37, Local 983 Photographs (PHOTOS 263)
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, District Council 37, Local 1306 Records (WAG 290)
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, District Council 37, Local 1930, New York Public Library Guild Photographs (PHOTOS 17)
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, District Council 37, Local 1930, New York Public Library Guild, Records (WAG 040)
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Workers, District Council 37, Local 1930: Ray Markey Files (WAG 286)
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, District Council 37: Ken Nash Audio Materials (OH 64)
Social Service Employees Union Records (WAG 3)
Social Service Employees Union Photographs (PHOTOS 14)
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, District Council 1707 Records (WAG 298)
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees (AFSCME), District Council 37 Printed Ephemera Collection (PE 020)
Historical/Biographical Note
District Council 37 was chartered by the American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees (AFSCME) in November 1944, bringing together a group of small locals representing municipal employees of New York City. The Council began achieving significant growth after the arrival, in 1947, of Executive Director Jerry Wurf. Over the next five years, DC 37 formed 55 new locals or organizing committees. The union continued to grow through organizing, mergers, and consolidation. By 1957, the Council claimed a membership of 25,000 members in 33 city agencies and departments. The 1950s and early 1960s also witnessed increasing militancy on the part of DC 37 members, as workers struck at numerous city agencies.
When Wurf left DC 37 in 1964 to become president of AFSCME, his deputy, Calogero Taibi, became executive director. Taibi soon resigned due to ill health, however, and Victor Gotbaum (b. 1921), a Chicago-based AFSCME representative, stepped in to lead DC 37. In his first few years as Executive Director, Gotbaum dealt with a 28-day strike in 1965 by members working as caseworkers and in other capacities for New York City's Welfare Department, and the passing of New York State's Taylor Law in 1967, which prohibits state employees from striking. Gotbaum brought with him from Chicago a talented organizer, Lillian Roberts (b. 1928), who had been a nurse's aide and vocal shop steward prior to joining Gotbaum's AFSCME staff in Illinois. Roberts' success in organizing nurses' aides in city hospitals for DC 37's Local 420 helped to put the Council over the threshold needed for a citywide majority of career and salary plan employees, and membership surpassed 50,000 in 1967. Roberts was appointed Associate Director of the union in 1968.
DC 37 dealt with major challenges in the 1970s as New York City descended into a deep fiscal crisis, in which municipal workers suffered layoffs, wage freezes, and benefit reductions. In spite of these difficult years, DC 37 nevertheless managed to surpass the 100,000-member mark in 1975.
The 1980s witnessed significant leadership changes at DC 37. In 1986, Victor Gotbaum retired after twenty-one years as Executive Director, during which time DC 37 had become the country's largest union of municipal workers. He was succeeded by Local 371 SSEU leader Stanley Hill.
The Council faced some difficult challenges in the late 1990s, when investigations by the Manhattan District Attorney revealed multiple instances of corruption inside the Council and its locals. AFSCME placed DC 37 in a trusteeship and Stanley Hill took a leave of absence in December 1998 and retired in early 1999. In 2002, Lillian Roberts was elected to serve as Executive Director of DC 37, returning after a twenty-year absence. Her election ended the trusteeship of DC 37 and returned control of the Council to its executive director, executive board, and delegates.
Throughout its history, DC 37 has actively embraced social movement unionism by linking its struggles for higher wages and benefits to other economic, social, and political issues. DC 37 sent a large delegation to the March on Washington in August 1963, and participated in numerous other demonstrations against segregation and discrimination; the Council and its members also protested against the Vietnam War.
In the 1980s, the Council continued its social activism, taking a leading role in convincing New York City's pension system to divest itself of stocks from companies doing business in apartheid South Africa. Recognizing its diverse membership demographics, DC 37 began union-wide celebrations of Black History Month, recognized other ethnic groups, and formed a Disability Advisory Committee in 1982, followed by activities for Women's History Month, a public stance in favor of gay rights, and programs for Puerto Rican Heritage.
Scope and Content Note
This collection is comprised of black and white photographic prints (the bulk are 8x10), color photographic prints (mainly 4x6 snapshots), contact sheets, negatives, and slides from the Communications Department of AFSCME District Council 37. There are approximately 41,300 photographs and 24,500 contact sheets. The collection contains approximately 422,400 individual negative images. The bulk of individual images are black and white negatives.
Series I: Public Employee Press Files, [1959]-[2001].
This series contains the photographic files of DC 37's official newspaper, Public Employee Press (PEP). First published on June 12, 1959, Public Employee Press has been published bi-weekly except for one issue per month in January and in the summer through most of its history.
Photographs are arranged by issue, in chronological order. Early issues are scattered from 1959 to 1967; there is a solid run from March 8, 1967 (Vol. 8, No. 3) to May 2001 (Vol. 42, No. 5). Most of the images are undated, but most were presumably shot close to publication date (except in cases where photographs were selected for use in historical retrospective issues). The majority of PEP photographs were taken in New York City, with a few shot in Albany, as well as at major rallies and marches in Washington. PEP files do not always include every image published in a particular issue, nor were all the photographs in these files necessarily published in PEP. There are multiple shots of single events, for example, only a few of which were reproduced in the newspaper.
The bulk of the images are 8x10 black and white photographic prints; color photographs begin to appear in the late 1990s, and files from 2000 on contain primarily 4x6 color snapshots. Many images contain production markings or attached instructions. While numerous photographs in the PEP's files were shot specifically for PEP, either by staff or freelance photographers (many of the earlier images were shot by veteran labor photographer Sam Reiss), the series also includes some images obtained from wire service agencies such as Wide World Photos and UPI, as well as various New York City newspapers.
PEP photographs primarily record DC 37 events, personalities, and programs; there is also some coverage of local, national, and international events of concern to the Council. DC 37 events documented include strikes, demonstrations, and rallies (including those supporting other labor unions); conferences, meetings, installations of officers, elections, press conferences, hearings, negotiations, and awards ceremonies; there are also numerous photographs of Council-sponsored heritage and cultural celebrations of Black History Month, Latino Heritage Month, Women's History Month and others (see additional subjects in Appendix 1). Programs and services covered include those for members, such as high school equivalency exam preparation classes, nurses' training and training upgrades, health and safety training, Quality of Work Life (QWL) (worksite improvement), and the Council's legal and health services, as well as programs and activities for members' families including Family Day, dance and art classes, sports, summer camp, holiday celebrations, and travel. In addition, PEP photographs profile locals, members, and workplaces, as well as individual members' work and personal lives; files also include publicity shots for plays, films, and television broadcasts of interest to DC 37.
Personalities consist of DC 37's leaders and officers, including Executive Directors Jerry Wurf, Victor Gotbaum, Stanley Hill, and Lillian Roberts (most images of Roberts date from before she became Executive Director, when she was a union organizer, and then Associate Director), local presidents and officers, as well as a large number of national and local politicians.
Local, national, and international news events and issues are also reflected in PEP photographs, including political campaigns and endorsements on both the local and national levels, safety, housing, and crime in New York City, national concerns such as the Vietnam War, environment, drugs, health care, HIV/AIDS, inflation, consumer affairs, and international issues such as the conflict in El Salvador and apartheid.
Researchers looking for images depicting specific topics or individuals should consult the PEP index created by DC 37, and covering the years 1966 - 2006 and issues of Public Employee Press, most of which is available at the Tamiment Library (in hard copy from 1966 through the present, in newspaper box #'s 347-356; copies from 1970 to 1978 are also on microfilm in microfilm collection # R-7618). Issues that contain historical retrospectives and heritage celebrations are good sources for images of Council-sponsored heritage and cultural celebrations such as Black History Month or Latino Heritage events. Appendix 1 contains a list of these PEP special issues.
Series II: Locals Files, 1948-2002.
This series is organized by local number, then chronologically within each local. Not all locals in DC 37 are represented in this series; approximately 85% of identified current and historic locals have some photos in this series. Designations are listed on the first file title for each local. Locals listed as "defunct" have either been merged or absorbed into existing locals with different names and numbers or rendered obsolete. (See Appendix 2 for locals list.)
The bulk of locals' photographs are black and white prints; many images were shot for or used in locals' newsletters (these are filed separately within each local); some images were also published in brochures and booklets. A number of images in this series were shot for or appeared in DC 37's first publication, Spotlight, which ran from 1947-1959 and was replaced by Public Employee Press.
Locals' photographs document events such as demonstrations, rallies, strikes, conferences, meetings, elections and installations, negotiations, and work on political campaigns, as well as social and recreational events. The files also include numerous officers' and members' individual and group portraits. Images of members on the job and workplace conditions can also be found for many locals. A few photographs also depict workplace equipment.
Series III: DC 37 History, [1946]-[1994].
Photographs in this series primarily depict specific events in DC 37's history, its officers and members. The bulk of the images are 8x10 black and white photographic prints. Many were shot by the labor photographer Sam Reiss; other photographers include Alexander Archer and Mildred Grossman. Many images in this series were shot for or appeared in Spotlight. Images of some of the same events documented in this series (as well as many historic events that are not represented in this series) may also be found in the Public Employee Press (PEP) files in Series I, in issue files following event dates, as well as files for issues with DC 37 historical retrospectives (particularly several commemorating the Council's 50th anniversary in 1994). Locals' files (Series II) also contain some images of DC 37 historic events.
Subseries III: A: Events, [1946]-1993.
Events are arranged chronologically. They include strikes, demonstrations, rallies and marches (including those in support of other unions); conferences, meetings, elections, and installations of officers and members. Most took place in the 1950s and 1960s. Notable images include those of key events in the Council's history, such as the Department of Parks election in 1956, the "Bermuda Day" rally in 1959, and city employees' mass rally at Madison Square Garden in 1967. Prints of the 1961 zoo strike depict workers on the picket line posed with various zoo animals. This series also contains images of major civil rights events (and DC 37's participation in them), including the 1963 March on Washington, the 1965 march in Montgomery, Alabama, and marches and rallies in Memphis following the assassination of Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. in 1968.
Subseries III: B: DC 37 Officers and Staff, 1955-1993.
Officers include folders on Executive Directors (especially numerous are those of Jerry Wurf; images of Lillian Roberts pre-date her tenure as Executive Director), followed by other officers, and staff, arranged in alphabetical order where identified. See Appendices 3 and 4 for lists of identified officers and staff.
Subseries III: C: DC 37 Members, 1956-[1994].
These files include several folders of images of rank and file DC 37 members, most of which show members on the job, arranged chronologically.
Subseries III: D: AFSCME, [1955]-1990.
Photographs in this series depict DC 37's parent organization AFSCME (American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees), including former AFSCME president Arnold Zander, and other district Councils, especially the now-defunct New York State District Council 50.
Subseries III: E: Other Individuals/Organizations, 1956-1989.
This series contains images of other individuals and organizations, not all labor-related, as well as politicians and civil rights leaders.
Subseries III: F: Portraits: Partial or No Identification, 1948-1987.
Individual and group portraits, in which persons may be identified by name, but their role within or relationship to DC 37 is unclear.
Series IV: DC 37 Subject Files, 1957-2000.
This series contains images documenting DC 37's programs, committees, associations and specific concerns. Several folders relate to the Council's Quality of Work Life (QWL) Program--labor-management committees that address worksite improvement and empowerment issues, and sponsor education and health fairs, lunchtime seminars, and employee recognition events. Some files contain photographs that illustrated Council newsletters, as well as those of the newsletter published by the QWL Committee. Most of the images are 8x10 black and white prints.
Series V: General Subject Files, 1966-1989.
Images in this series depict a miscellany of topics that are not directly related to DC 37, such as "Animals," "Children," and "New York City History."
Series VI: Contact Sheets, [1958]-[2001].
Subseries VI: A: Numbered Contact Sheets, 1982-2000.
This subseries contains a nearly complete run of numbered contact sheets from 1982–2000. Many of these sheets contain images that were published in issues of the Public Employee Press (some in fact are duplicates of contact sheets found in Subseries B--PEP Contact Sheets), but in most cases the specific issue number or date of publication is not designated. Most contact sheets numbered from 4312 to 8551 have matching negatives in the numbered negatives subseries.
The Council used several different numbering schemes over the years for its contact sheets and negatives. The contact sheets in this subseries, arranged in numerical order, follow a scheme begun by DC 37 in Oct 1970 with a "DC" prefix (usually absent from later contact sheets). However, some of these contact sheets also have a "GR" or "CO" designation number on their reverse sides, in addition to the "DC" number. Researchers looking for matching negatives for images on these contact sheets should search under both of the designations in the numbered negatives subseries.
Subseries VI: B: Public Employee Press Contact Sheets, [1967]-[2001].
These contact sheets contain multiple shots of individual PEP events, only a few of which (sometimes none) were actually published in PEP. While it varies from issue to issue, most photographs in the PEP prints series (Series I) have corresponding images on contact sheets in this subseries, but not all contact sheets in this subseries have matching images in the PEP files.
Many of these contact sheets also have matching negatives in the collection. For PEP contact sheets from 1967-1970, matching negatives may be found in the PEP Negatives subseries and can be identified by corresponding numbers in brackets found on reverse of contact sheets and on negative sleeves. After 1970, matching negatives for contact sheets in this subseries are most likely to be found in the Numbered Negatives subseries.
Subseries VI: C: Locals Contact Sheets, [1958]-1999.
Images in this subseries are arranged by specific locals (in local number order), and correspond to some of the images in Locals photograph files (Series II). Not all locals have contact sheet files.
Many of the sheets in this subseries also have matching negatives in Subseries E (Locals) of Series VII: Negatives under corresponding local numbers. Some have an original subject or other designation that corresponds to one listed in a negative file title (i.e. "Local 420—City Hospitals Exposes"). Matching negatives for numbered contact sheets in this subseries can also be found in the Numbered Negatives subseries.
Subseries VI: D: DC 37 History Contact Sheets, [1958]-1995.
Most of the images in this subseries correspond to the prints in the DC 37 History photographs series (Series III), which focuses on specific events, individuals, and organizations in DC 37 history, while a few files (particularly for civil rights events) also contain images not found in Series III. Numbered contact sheets in this subseries may have corresponding negatives in the Numbered Negatives subseries. Some history contact sheets have matching negatives in Series VII, Subseries G (DC 37 History Negatives), which may be identified by similar file titles. For example, nearly complete sets of matching negatives can be found for contact sheets depicting the post-King assassination marches in Memphis, and for those contact sheets in the AFSCME: DC 50 file.
Subseries VI: E: DC 37 Subject Files Contact Sheets, 1963-1996.
Contact sheets relating to DC 37 programs, committees, associations and specific concerns of the Council. Most contain Quality of Work Life (QWL) images. A small number of matching negatives can be found in the Subject Files Negatives subseries, and numbered contact sheets in this subseries may have corresponding negatives in the Numbered Negatives subseries.
Subseries VI: F: General Subject Files Contact Sheets, 1973-1974.
Sheets in this subseries correspond to many of the photographic prints in the General Subject Files series.
Series VII: Negatives, [1948]-[2003].
The bulk of negatives in the collection are 35 mm, with some in the 120 format, a smaller number in the 4x5 format, and a few larger-size formats. There are approximately 422,400 individual negative images in this series (approximately 422,000 35 mm and 120 images; 400 4x5 negatives).
Each collection box contains four negative boxes. Locations for negatives in boxes 57-59 also include specific negative box numbers (listed as "carton" number).
Subseries VII: A: Numbered Negatives, 1970–[2002].
The bulk of numbered negatives are from the "DC" numbering scheme (these match the contact sheets in numbered contact sheets), arranged numerically. "DC" numbers are followed by "GR" and "CO" numbers; also included are a small number of scattered numbered negatives. Most are 35mm, with some 120 format. DC, GR, and CO runs are mostly complete; there are occasional gaps in sequencing.
Subseries VII: B: Numbered 4x5 Negatives, [1971]–[1987].
A small number of 4x5 numbered negatives.
Subseries VII: C: Public Employee Press Negatives, [1967]-[2001].
Negatives in this subseries are 35mm or 120 and correspond to PEP photographic print and contact sheet files. The bulk of negatives from 1967-1970 match contact sheets in the PEP contact sheets subseries. Matches are identified within issues by shoot numbers in brackets, found on reverse of contact sheets and on matching negative sleeves. Negatives for snapshots in late PEP photograph files (1999-2002) in Series I are also in this subseries.
Subseries VII: D: PEP 4x5 Negatives, [1969]-[2000].
One-hundred-five 4x5 negatives from scattered issues of PEP.
Subseries VII: E: Locals Negatives, [1967]-[1999].
The bulk of these negatives are in 35mm, with some 120 negatives. They are arranged numerically by local number; most have matching contact sheets in the Locals Contact Sheets subseries.
Subseries VII: F: Locals 4x5 Negatives, [1963]-[1968].
Forty-five 4x5 negatives from scattered locals.
Subseries VII: G: DC 37 History Negatives, [1963]-[1972].
Arrangement mirrors that of subseries in Series III: DC 37 History. The bulk of these 35mm and 120 negatives depict specific events, particularly the post-Martin Luther King assassination marches in Memphis. There are also numerous negatives that match the AFSCME: DC 50 contact sheets in the DC 37 History Contact Sheets subseries.
Subseries VII: H: DC 37 History 4x5 Negatives, [1948]-[1989].